<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Advanced Server Setup on NetBSD 3.0 with Pkgsrc 2006Q2</title>

  <subtitle>This document is aimed at gathering the best way to set up a
  NetBSD 3.0 based server that offers all services needed by ISPs and hosters
  (web server (SSL-capable), mail server (with SMTP-AUTH and TLS), DNS server,
  FTP server, PostgresQL server, POP3/IMAP, etc.).</subtitle>

  <section>
    <title>Advanced Server Requirements</title>

    <para>For the following, I assume that you have already properly setup a
    server as described <ulink url="???">here</ulink>.</para>

    <para>I will also assume that you have an internet connection and a
    router-modem connected to it, so we wont bother about the modem
    connections settings. more information is available in the <ulink
    url="http://www.netbsd.org/guide/en/">NetBSD Guide.</ulink></para>

    <para>The mostly used configuration in that case is that you have an IP
    address assigned by your ISP whenever you establish your
    connection.</para>

    <table>
      <title>Features needed and software used</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">Feature</entry>

            <entry align="center">Implementation</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>SSH - for remote console access</entry>

            <entry>OpenSSH (base)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>DNS - for name resolution, so you can forget the IP
            address</entry>

            <entry>BIND (???)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>NTP - for date / time automatic setup</entry>

            <entry>ntpd (base)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>SMTP - to be able to send mails from your server</entry>

            <entry>Postfix (???)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>IMAP - to be able to access your mails on your
            server</entry>

            <entry>Cyrus (???)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>POP3 - to be able to retrieve your mails from your
            server</entry>

            <entry>???</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>FTP - to be able to quickly access your files on your
            server</entry>

            <entry>wsFTPd (pkgsrc)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>HTTP - to be able to have a web page exposed to the world
            ;-)</entry>

            <entry>Apache (pkgsrc) v2</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>PHP - to be able to have more complex web pages :-p</entry>

            <entry>Ap-PHP (pkgsrc)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>SQL - to host a database, usefull for complex
            applications</entry>

            <entry>PostgresQL (pkgsrc) v8.0.8, PhpPgAdmin (pkgsrc)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Server Administration</entry>

            <entry>Webmin (pkgsrc) and modules...</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para></para>

    <para>For any comments and feedback, I would like to hear from you, so
    send me a <ulink url="mailto:asmodehn@gna.org">mail</ulink> ;-)</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Pkgsrc Setup</title>

    <para>I will not describe here the pkgsrc structure, features and
    behaviour. You should already be familiar with it. If you are not, you can
    read the <ulink url="http://www.netbsd.org/Documentation/pkgsrc/">pkgsrc
    guide</ulink>.</para>

    <para>However it is good to remind here that the pkgsrc collection can be
    configured, that is customise the way building and installing packages
    will behave.</para>

    <para>If you have installed the basic NetBSD described <ulink
    url="???">here</ulink> You should already have configured the cpuflags
    package to optimise your builds depending on your hardware. Just make sure
    the optimisation you setup are safe.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Another option that can be usefull when setting up a server, is the
    one controlling the rc.d scripts. To automatically copy the rc.d scripts
    that comes with a package to /etc/rc.d you should add :</para>

    <programlisting>PKG_RCD_SCRIPTS=YES</programlisting>

    <para>to your /etc/mk.conf.</para>

    <para>However I usually prefer symbolic linkage to keep in mind where the
    file actually comes from...</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SSH Setup</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>DNS Setup</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>NTP Setup</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO</emphasis></para>

    <section>
      <title>Client only</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>NTP Server</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mail : SMTP, IMAP, POP3</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO</emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>FTP Server</title>

    <para>First, you need to install the proftpd package using pkgsrc :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; cd /usr/pkgsrc/net/proftpd
&gt; make &amp;&amp; make install</programlisting>

    <para>If your build and installation was successful, TODO</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>If you wish to start the ProFTPd server at boottime, you need to add
    proftpd=YES to your /etc/rc.conf.</para>

    <para>Using the rc.d script, you can start the server just like that
    :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; /etc/rc.d/proftpd start</programlisting>

    <para>To stop the server, substitute start with stop.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Apache Setup</title>

    <para>First, you need to install the apache package using pkgsrc :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; cd /usr/pkgsrc/www/apache2
&gt; make &amp;&amp; make install</programlisting>

    <para>If your build and installation was successful, you should now edit
    the Apache configuration file /usr/pkg/etc/httpd/httpd.conf to fit your
    needs. At least set your Servername.</para>

    <para>I usually authorise my users to have their own website. To do that
    you need to uncomment those lines :</para>

    <programlisting>#
# Control access to UserDir directories.  The following is an example
# for a site where these directories are restricted to read-only.
#
&lt;Directory /home/*/public_html&gt;
    AllowOverride FileInfo AuthConfig Limit Indexes
    Options MultiViews Indexes SymLinksIfOwnerMatch IncludesNoExec
    &lt;Limit GET POST OPTIONS PROPFIND&gt;
        Order allow,deny
        Allow from all
    &lt;/Limit&gt;
    &lt;LimitExcept GET POST OPTIONS PROPFIND&gt;
        Order deny,allow
        Deny from all
    &lt;/LimitExcept&gt;
&lt;/Directory&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Note : Since Apahce 2.2, you can just uncomment the line which
    include the user directory config.</para>

    <para>If you wish to start the Apache Webserver at boottime, you need to
    add apache=yes to your /etc/rc.conf.</para>

    <para>You could now start, stop and restart the Apache Webserver using
    apachectl like that :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; apachectl start</programlisting>

    <para>Or using the rc.d script if you enabled it, just like that :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; /etc/rc.d/apache start</programlisting>

    <para>To stop the server, substitute start with stop. If you're running a
    production server, you should pay attention to the graceful option.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Once the server is started, you can connect to it with any browser,
    using your IP adress or the server name you setup.</para>

    <para>For example locally :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; links 127.0.0.1</programlisting>

    <para>This way you can make sure it works before going on with the next
    step.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>If you want one of your exisiting user to be able to easily manage
    webpages, just add him to the www group like that:</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; usermod -G www <replaceable>&lt;userlogin&gt;</replaceable></programlisting>

    <para>This is sometimes needed when users want to hack around with their
    own blogs or wiki manually.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>PHP Setup</title>

    <para></para>

    <para>First, you need to get the Apache module for PHP (version 5.1.4)
    installed on your machine :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; cd /usr/pkgsr/www/ap-php
&gt; make &amp;&amp; make install</programlisting>

    <para>Once the build and the installation is fine, and as explicited by
    the installation message, you need to setup the php module, and the
    handler in your apache configuration.</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; vim /usr/pkg/etc/httpd/httpd.conf</programlisting>

    <para></para>

    <programlisting>#
# Dynamic Shared Object (DSO) Support
#
[...]
LoadModule php5_module /usr/pkg/lib/httpd/mod_php5.so
AddHandler application/x-httpd-php .php</programlisting>

    <para>And if you want to have a default php page, you will need to add
    index.php to your DirectoryIndex :</para>

    <programlisting>#
# DirectoryIndex: sets the file that Apache will serve if a directory is requested
[...]
DirectoryIndex index.php index.html index.html.var</programlisting>

    <para></para>

    <para>To test if PHP is working, create a small file in your Document Root
    Directory (this is by default /usr/pkg/share/httpd/htdocs) called
    test.php</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; vim /usr/pkg/share/httpd/htdocs/test.php</programlisting>

    <para>This file needs to contain only one line with the function phpinfo()
    :</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;? phpinfo() ?&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Open your Browser and point it to this URL:</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; links http://127.0.0.1/test.php</programlisting>

    <para>You should now see a Website with information regarding your PHP
    installation.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>You can now install extension to PHP like to handle zip archive for
    example :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; cd /usr/pkgsr/archivers/php-zip
&gt; make &amp;&amp; make install</programlisting>

    <para>If the build and installation were fine, and as explicited in the
    installation message, you need now to enable the extension:</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; vim /usr/pkg/etc/php.ini</programlisting>

    <para></para>

    <programlisting>;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;
; Dynamic Extensions ;
;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;
[...]
extension=zip.so</programlisting>

    <para>After restarting the server the extension should be displayed in
    your test page.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>PostgresQL Server Setup</title>

    <para></para>

    <para>As usual we will first need to install postgresql80 from pkgsrc.
    This version has been chosen mainly because of the version expected by
    phppgadmin, that we will install later on.</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; cd /usr/pkgsr/databases/postgresql80
&gt; make &amp;&amp; make install</programlisting>

    <para>If the build and installation were fine, you should now add
    pgsql=yes to your /etc/rc.conf.</para>

    <para>You could now start the PostgresQL server using postmaster, or
    better, using the rc.d script if you enabled it, just like that :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; /etc/rc.d/pgsql start</programlisting>

    <para>This will take care of the initial setup for you ;-)</para>

    <para>To stop the server, just substitute start with stop as usual.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>I strongly advise you to install phpPgAdmin to administrate your
    database. It makes the work easier. However to be quite secure, phpPgAdmin
    doesnt authorise the default user pgsql to login.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Here is how we will setup the PostgresQL installation to be secure
    and usable with a "database administrator" login in phpPgAdmin :</para>

    <para></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>PostgresQL is by default configured to "trust" local user, that
        means they dont need to enter any password. But as we will have a
        website to access it, that will soon become a problem.</para>

        <para>We first need to reconfigure the PostgresQL administrator (user
        pgsql) to have a password.</para>

        <programlisting>&gt; su pgsql
$ psql -c "ALTER USER pgsql WITH PASSWORD '<replaceable>newpassword</replaceable>'" -d template1
$ exit</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Then we need to reconfigure the server to ask for a password,
        even for local users :</para>

        <programlisting>&gt; vim /usr/pkg/pgsql/data/pg_hba.conf</programlisting>

        <programlisting># TYPE  DATABASE    USER        CIDR-ADDRESS          METHOD

# "local" is for Unix domain socket connections only
local   all         all                               md5
# IPv4 local connections:
host    all         all         127.0.0.1/32          md5
# IPv6 local connections:
host    all         all         ::1/128               md5</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Now restart your server to apply the changes :</para>

        <programlisting>&gt; /etc/rc.d/pgsql restart</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>phpPgAdmin Setup</title>

    <para>As usual we will first need to install phppgadmin from
    pkgsrc.</para>

    <para>This will also install the correct version of PostgresQL clients
    (8.0.8) if needed, along with the PostgresQL module for PHP.</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; cd /usr/pkgsr/databases/phppgadmin
&gt; make &amp;&amp; make install</programlisting>

    <para>If the build and installation were fine, and as explicited by the
    install message, you should now enable the PostgresQL Module for PHP
    :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; vim /usr/pkg/etc/php.ini</programlisting>

    <programlisting>;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;
; Dynamic Extensions ;
;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;;
[...]
extension=pgsql.so</programlisting>

    <para>And you need to setup the phppgadmin website :</para>

    <para></para>

    <programlisting>&gt; vim /usr/pkg/etc/httpd/httpd.conf</programlisting>

    <programlisting>[...]
Include /usr/pkg/share/examples/phppgadmin/apache.conf</programlisting>

    <para></para>

    <para>You need to restart the apache server to make sure everything is
    setup :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; /etc/rc.d/apache restart</programlisting>

    <para>Then you can connect to your brand new website to administrate your
    database to the phppgadmin website. As an example locally :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; links http://localhost/phppgadmin/</programlisting>

    <para>Hint : Dont forget the trailing slash...</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>At this point you should not be able to login as pgsql. To enable
    this just edit /usr/pkg/share/phppgadmin/config.inc.php and set the extra
    login security to false :</para>

    <programlisting>&gt; vim /usr/pkg/share/phppgadmin/config.inc.php</programlisting>

    <programlisting>// If extra login security is true, then logins via phpPgAdmin with no
// password or certain usernames (pgsql, postgres, root, administrator)
// will be denied. Only set this false once you have read the FAQ and
// understand how to change PostgreSQL's pg_hba.conf to enable
// passworded local connections.
$conf['extra_login_security'] = false;</programlisting>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Please make sure you have enable md5 password
    authentication in the PostgresQL Server as explicited before
    !!!</emphasis></para>

    <para>I would really appreciate any feedback on this section and the best
    way to setup a secure postgresQL / phpPgAdmin since my experience with
    databases and PostgresQL is quite limited. Just drop me a <ulink
    url="mailto:asmodehn_AT_gna_DOT_org">mail</ulink>, thanks a lot !</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Now you should be able to login as pgsql with the password you
    specified earlier on. This way you can easily create databases for blogs,
    wikis, etc.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</article>